嗰個表列。
person。
咁嗰度咧就呢個表廿二咧。
睇一睇，帶大家去誒睇一睇第五十二頁嗰個表廿二嗰度先。
將二零零五至二零一年究竟係用咗幾多個誒？
好嚇噉啊！Kenneth誒，我哋主打嘅議員麥煥，你開始好唔好？多謝主席誒。
開原因，我哋或者要開多次會添，誒，因為依個情況，我哋都唔想見到，先向你道歉嚇，誒。
價值係幾多錢啊？用咗，但係我想知可唔可以好易將呢個表廿二嘅依資料係變為一個誒？
其實即係個工作量咧，喺呢十年間係大增嘅。但係咧，喺睇呢一個表之餘咧，我哋睇到呢一個咧，誒係一個即係誒。
人數喺度，我先向局長同埋呢班同事先向你道歉。誒，因為今日延遲咗，我哋特別嘅情況啊，司長嚟解釋呢個西九個佢哋個誒Palace Museum嗰度嚇。噉我唔好意思，我哋今日咧就希望可以誒搭九就開完呢個會。但係如果我哋未開，
director，唔好意思嚇。啊，今日我哋係去到誒第四部分嚇。第四部分嗰度咧就講關於係依個管治嘅問題，但係大家喺你枱面嗰度，應該你琴晚已經收到Jane七八九㗎啦。依個七八九去誒直。
係政府回應我哋誒早幾早次開會嘅提出嚟嘅問題，佢都答得好好清楚㗎啦。如果大家都需要誒問依啲問題，我諗我哋問完第四部分先，翻翻轉頭問嗰啲誒其他嘅問題喺依個J七八九嗰度，好唔好？
唔好意思，先首先就係即係延遲咗今次嘅會議。咁咧都係主席講有特別情況啦。咁誒呢一度咧，我哋去去到呢一個嘅第二章嘅誒第四部分啦，就係關於即係誒U G C嗰個管治問題。咁當然亦都包括有。
佢嘅誒成員嘅出席率啊，誒個支出啊，誒或者開會嘅規矩啊、記錄等等。噉我都希望咧，我哋誒呢一度嘅各位同事咧都可以根據翻，即係佢哋誒有興趣嘅議題喺呢個章節度發問。不過，首先咧，我都想睇。
即係。
多謝你問。
Yes, well, Chairman, thank you for the.
教資會、研資局同埋質保局喺每一年入邊。
唔係唔同機構、唔同嘅教資局、研資局同埋質保局開會。
Let me take those items in turn. Yes, the three councils. The UGC meets in January.
每日房價由一千四百蚊至到三千三百蚊不等，咁平均就一千八百三十蚊啦。咁咧？
April, stroke, May, and September. RGC, sorry, QAC meets in those months as well.
誒，sorry，應該係幾多room night嗰個statistic有冇可以容唔容易extract到出嚟咧？呢一個嘅information。
都要book幾多間房啦？你畀個大啲discount我，即係有冇呢啲噉嘅arrangement咧？主席，唔該。局長，你想邊個答啊？啊，主席，我想請阿Richard答一答。Doctor Richard Armour。
誒，佢哋係book咗幾多個room night或者night room whatever啦嚇，即係個statistics有冇咧？其實有可唔可以做到啊？主席，我相信誒教資會係有呢個資料嘅。係噉，麻煩你哋誒用後畀翻我哋，即係我都想睇一睇嗰個。
係列出咗教資會、教資會屬下嘅研資局同埋質保局嘅一個嘅誒會議開支噉，即係睇到嗰個情況咧，都係由二零零五年起至到二零一五年止咧，咁都係即係一路上升緊。當然我都知道咧，因為。
嗱，我唔知呢個包唔包括呢呢一個嘅誒住宿嘅費用每晚。阿阿阿沈介處長或者阿主席可唔可以代我？好啊，問一問沈介處長。沈介處長，你可唔可以答答表份啊？誒，應該嘅包括咗。包括嚇。嗱，如果係噉樣樣嘅時候，可唔可以幫我將呢個表嘅information咧，即係個。
Trend個情況係點樣樣嗱？我我知道咧，其實誒。Dr. Richard Butler， you understand what was being asked and can you provide the information later? Thank you, Chairman. Yes, it's one of these things we can we can provide the members with. I'm sure it may take a little time, but after the meeting, we can break that down into room nights and.
trend，所以你先。Yes，OK，OK。嗱噉，由於咧，因為我都開頭而家開始就講緊嗰個個支出先啦。噉，但係其實其他同時可以就其他嘅嘅誒一啲管治問題提出意見。不過我我我由嗰個即係支出嗰度開開始着手先啦，主席誒咁嗱誒，我哋。
喺五廿頁講咗個表啦，噉就睇翻隔離嗰度咧，都係講緊一啲嘅誒酒店啊、住宿安排等等嘅。咁誒四點一六嗰度咧，就有一啲嘅數字，就係話咧誒，比如四點一六嗰度講，就所有房間晚數嘅。
嗯。
happy to do that.
which I'm sure you'll come to you'll come to later.
RGC meets in December and June.
誒，報告嘅四十六頁第四點四段。
是是更為困難，所以這係關於關於時間。
The timing of the meetings is largely driven by the academic calendar.
好，好啦，噉我都再繼續問翻嗰個誒一啲開支嘅問題啦。噉我哋睇翻誒。
Is have you made arrangement with the five hotels on guarantee room nights, or have you?
That's all I remember, Jim。啊，我想問一問主席，嗯，你哋選擇呢五間酒店係咪因為佢嗰個誒誒位置咧？即係我想問一問呢啲位置，呢啲五間酒店我唔想開名啊，但係係咪喺中環同埋金鐘？你有冇諗過灣仔或者銅鑼灣都係好近啫，其實都係咪？啊，Doctor Richard，阿。
審計處長亦都留意到咧，呢啲嘅酒店嘅誒報價咧，都係來自五間高級嘅酒店嗱。當然個背景我唔係好清楚，我就想第即係想啊，主席，當我向誒局方問一問咧，究竟誒你哋開會嗱三個唔同嘅都。
你哋開會嘅時候係每一年嘅幾多月咧？同埋你哋開會地點喺邊度咧？同埋你哋即係有冇去嘗試過用不同嘅酒店攞一個即係報價咧？同埋你哋有冇試過啊同一啲酒店做一啲arrangement，即係話我哋guarantee每年。
The timetable of universities, particularly for RGC, we try to vary the dates to make them more convenient for allocating grants. June and September is not June and December is not ideal. However, the overseas members just simply cannot come. They can get time off, they can take leave in June and December, but other months.
the the location the location of meetings is in our offices in Wan Chai Harbour Road, and you asked about different hotels. Certainly, as the audit noted, we had since 2009 we had been pretty much asking for prices from the five regular hotels. Recently.
for the January meetings, for example, we've added four to that. So now we're asking for we're seeking quotations from nine hotels. But I think in principle we're taking advice from the from the government logistics department about how best to procure hotel rooms and also air tickets.
Understand. Yes, Chairman, through you. Yes, they're they're close to our location. That was one of the the principal reasons for choosing the the five and now nine hotels. I think yes. The the second part of the honourable Kenneth Long's question.
Accept some special rates for them for an exchange of guarantee notes. Thank you. I had forgotten that part of the question. We haven't entered into annual rates with the hotels. We do tender. We do ask for quotations well in advance. We've noted anecdotally. I've certainly noted the prices vary.
doctor doctor阿媽。
好，Thank you, Chairman.
Okay. Thank, thank you, Chairman. Through you.
好啦，除咗呢一啲嘅誒年度嘅酬金之外咧。
是係個政策 issue， set by UGC 或 the Education Bureau。
have remained the same since the since the same inflation factor is is is attached every year. That's as as much as I know.
the the the the levels are adjusted every year in terms of the the government pay award, the same rates.
as the government's pay award, but how they were set originally is long long before my time, and I guess certainly the differentials.
點樣set同埋你哋有咩機制去去去即係調整佢嘅咧？咁調整嘅時候又有啲乜嘢嘅誒制度底下去調整啊？根據啲乜嘢嘢去去調整嘅咧？嚇，唔該，Dr. Richard。
淨係非本地評審委員先有咧？呢一個嘅做法係咪所有即係類似嘅誒學術評審機構外國嘅都係淨係畀非本地嘅評審委員咧呢啲嘅酬金？
Education works when you act as an external examiner overseas. You're paid not by the hour. You're paid an honorarium. It's part of professional cooperation, and I guess that's the same reason. But usually, not usually local members of funding bodies are not remunerated, as far as I know.
so much, according to weeks and months in the year, whether a hotel would be able to enter into a corporate arrangement with us, that's something I'd be more than happy to explore, and certainly again we'll take advice from from those colleagues and other bureaus who are expert in procurement. We're more
誒嗰度列出咗咧教資會嘅成員、研資局嘅成員，同埋誒其他嘅成員啦。教育委員小組委員會嘅成員都都每年咧都有獲發一筆嘅誒，即係叫津貼又好，或者係酬金啦。咁呢啲都係啊，非本地成員先先有。
啫咁嗱，第一樣嘢我問啊，如果你即係誒非本地評審委員係獲得呢啲酬金，咁但係點解我哋本地成員就冇咧？會唔會即係造成咗一種為即係我哋本地嘅成員可能冇乜太即係？當然呢個呢個酬金，我我我都覺得唔係話好多嘅。點解即係？
The the practice of overseas institutions varies, but in in higher education certainly the the usual, I can speak from my experience in Europe and Australia as well as here, is that non-local members are not remunerated. Although universities, let's say for a university council in Australia and in the UK, it's up to the council.
So usually that difference is maintained. Hong Kong members serving in university councils overseas or funding bodies overseas, which there are certainly examples, I believe, they would receive an honorarium similar to ours. That's in the same way that higher
Dr. Richard.
係，Doctor Richard。
O.K.，得。
如果啲誒，
價錢係幾多，同埋係咪每一個委員會？
Sarah will help me around 1,500.
嘅成員都係攞翻同一個amount嘅咧嚇。
誒，我哋睇翻第五十頁嘅四點一四段咧。
呢個係第二句嗰度講嘅，叫按日津貼。噉我想問一問咧，呢個按日津貼誒個誒？
Through you, the per diem allowance there there are two types of per diem allowance. The overseas members receive a per diem allowance, which is around.
委員啊，或者成員咧嚟香港開會嘅時候咧，就會令我知道咧，除咗住宿同機票之外咧，就會有個按日嘅津貼。
Around a thousand dollars per day, that's for their local expenses while they're while they're in Hong Kong. Local members are paid a travel allowance for attending meetings, and it's around two hundred dollars.
咁呢一個噉嘅安排，又係咪國際一啲嘅誒大學資助委員會嘅慣例咧？呢個畀一啲津貼去海外嘅委員參加呢個會議，係咪慣例嚟嘅咧？
你你你你有冇？你
好唔該，係主席。噉我想問一問啊，呢啲嘅誒酬金onirium嘅嘅嘅嘅level，比如話啊十七萬七千七百五十就係教資會非本地成員，跟住就九萬三千一百蚊就係研資局嘅成員。呢一啲嘅誒個amount都都唔係話好好公整嘅。咁究竟係點？
嗱，主席就開支嗰度咧，我我問咗咁多啦。噉我要轉一轉少少嘅話題咧，我我就要去翻第二個大嘅題目啦。喺呢個部分入邊咧，係關於一個利益衝突嘅誒問題，同埋處理嘅方法。咁呢個我哋都睇翻四十七頁。
第四點五同埋四點六段啦，咁主席，我諗你大概都即係我哋誒三數個禮拜之前就去呢一個誒研資會嗰度，即係UGC下低嘅一個嘅一個小誒小組委員會啦，噉就睇過佢哋處理利益衝突嘅嘅方。
打出去幾盎？
呢個餐，呢個餐。
暫時中，你未unlike兩套申報制度之前咧，都係要即係。
我想問問有冇成員又係UGC又係LGC嘅成員啊？係咪有嘅都。
Take on on where members come from, and the second tier is applied, as I said, virtually on a meeting-to-meeting, agenda item-to-agenda item basis.
制度同LGC係咪一些一樣嘅咧？如果唔係一些一樣嘅時候，就有啲咩啊分別咧嚇？唔該，Doctor Richard Armour。
Thank you. Thank you. Through you, you take a time. You because it takes some time for translation. There's no hurry. We have plenty of time. We might call another meeting. Doesn't matter.
Again, through you, Chairman. Thank you for the question. I believe that the the RGC practice is to have the the the annual.
叫做跟緊兩套少少唔同嘅制度，會唔會令到啲委員有有好多即係疑惑咧？如果噉樣樣，我希望即係你你澄清下呢樣嘢，同埋你可唔可以畀到個時間表我哋？如果你話想盡量將兩套申報制度拉，噉你幾時會做？幾時做到咧？
所以 hadn't declared, so the two-tier system is important. That we ask members, UGC and RGC, if there is any particular conflict in the item or on an agenda, they must declare, irrespective of their their first-tier declaration.
the the first tier level of declaration updated every every year. The UGCs has not been at to date, but we're happy to bring those in line. We'll still maintain the the two tier system. I think the practice has deviated simply because in RGC with the
法噉佢哋亦都有一個誒年度嘅誒update啊，或者如果有咩情況改變，佢都會即係要求誒UGC入邊嗰啲成員去去update佢嗰個噉嘅申報制度。嗱，我想問一問第一樣嘢咧，UGC入邊嘅嘅委員嘅嘅申報嗰個誒？
With the role of the council and particularly the panel members, this is so important. It changes constantly. In higher education, we're always cooperating with other universities. So a regular an annual declaration is insufficient, because you can make an annual declaration and a few months later work for a university you hadn't, or advise a university.
啊！
Well.
哈哈哈哈哈！
Doctor James。
個話題去。
好，主席，我我再誒繼續再將誒。
So just to put this on the record, and actually we have done this, but I just set a good example there. Okay, Kenneth.
I think we better set a good example. Decoration of interest. I'm a member of the court of the UST.
Council and Court of the Hong Kong U, so I'm Poh Poh Jie representing the Council, also a member of the Court.
擴闊些少，嗯，嗱，阿阿Cannibal對佢咧，頭先佢未答到呢個問題，即係話佢可以幾時可以即刻做到？等佢，嗯。
好，好嗱，咁誒，講咗支出嘅問題，亦都講咗一個利益衝突嘅問題啦。咁第三個層面咧，我就想講講。
renew呢一啲嘅委員嗰個任期嘅時候咧，你哋會唔會考慮佢哋嘅以往出席率嘅誒嘅嘅高又低咧，先正去去再委任佢哋咧？唔該。
Let me say from the April May meeting of UGC, which is which is apart from the meeting that starts on Monday, it'll be the next possible item that we can we can update the the first year declaration to an annual basis.
又有，即係尤其是提咗有一位就係得咗二十九個percent，咁另外一位咧就係有質保局嘅非本地成員咧，就係五十個percent。噉我想問一問啊，喺
The Honourable Kenneth Long asked you for a timetable that you're going to align the two system into one. So, what is your timetable? You said that you can do as soon as possible. What is the soonest possible? I think he give a date.
有冇common members between the UGC and RGC? Yes, there are deliberately so. For example, the chairman of RGC is an ex officio member of of UGC, and sometimes, but not always, there are appointed members on both on both councils, one or two.咁即係佢而家就。
Thank you for that. That would be very helpful. Aligning the system in terms of time, we can do that very quickly. I don't see any problem with aligning the and bringing UGC into line and QAC into line with with RGC in terms of the first tier declaration. Will that have any doubt in council members? I don't think so. We
Discuss conflict of interest on a regular basis, almost at every meeting, where we're asking the question. So aligning the first tier declaration will not trouble members at all, or put any doubts in in members, because the second tier is so strict. The first tier is simply, you know, a first taste, a first
誒。
especially。
開會嘅日期咧係誒。
埋即係關於帶埋太太先生或者同伴嘅問題啊！
睇到咧喺採購機票，尤其是喺第五十五頁嗰度咧。
嗱，我哋我哋每一次都即係我我知道，因因為其實你哋唔同嘅委員會嗰個誒。
另外一樣嘅個問題，我想問咧，就話亦都我知道咧，有一啲嘅海外委員咧，係要求帶埋佢嘅誒。
會唔同嘅，亦都因為噉樣嘅情況底下咧，你都要分好多次咧，係去採購個機票。嗱，但係我我想知道，其實你哋喺誒？
幫呢一啲海外委員訂機票嘅時候呢，你哋有冇誒根據一個誒準則去做嘅咧？你即即係分得好散，因為我見到你其實都都喺喺喺誒五頁嗰個表嗰度，咁究竟你係誒？
Thank you, Chairman. Through you, yes, is the simple answer. Yes, very much so. As as we recognise from the audit report, we concur. It's a sign of commitment. And if members are unable for whatever reason to commit, then we would consider that very. The question is very specific. You say yes. What had you done in the past?
啊，主席，我仲有一個啊問題關於支出嘅啫，咁之後我就會誒將個時間交畀我哋委員會嘅其他同事。嗱，嗰個就係關於嗰個即係機票嘅問題啦。呢個問題就係關於嗯嗱，我就。
誒成員或者委員之間嘅嘅出席率嘅問題啦，咁嗱表廿一嗰度咧都睇到咧嗰個出席率咧就即係大部分都係高嘅。咁但係四點八段亦都提到咧，有啲委員嘅出席率咧就係偏低。
In the past, it's very simple to answer yes. But understand, understand. I'm sorry. In the past, members have not been renewed. If I put it bluntly, for poor attendance, that has happened. And certainly in the cases cited, we will take that into account when the time for renewal.
太太或者伴侶或者先生啦嚇，伴侶啦嚇啊嚟香港嘅噉，你哋又即係都會有你哋嘅做法。我嘅誒解讀咧，都係你哋會喺嗰個不盡範圍內咧，你係可以畀佢，比如話將一張誒business class ticket咧就split開做兩張，即係普通嘅。
唔係 necessarily practised, but certainly allowed and and.
啊，financial limit of the cheapest available flight from， the the。
Both hotel rooms, but certainly airline tickets. Whether
And since it seems to us there is no extra cost, since we we always set.
My own experience serving on a council in Singapore was that that that was allowed.
Where they they are coming to attend a research assessment exercise panel or an RGC panel, that being able to bring a partner is a deal breaker.
阿主席，doctor Amor，頭先你講咧，你就話會誒徵詢嗰個誒我哋物流處嘅意見，就點樣去做好嗰個誒基建嘅procurement。
咁又點樣樣？即係似乎都好好複雜下咧。Ethics係一個非常複雜嘅課題，噉我都唔知你哋即係嗰個標準係點樣樣，可唔可以解釋下咧？嚇，主席，Richard。
the the partner ticket issue that has been practised for some time with certainly in our organisation. The reason being that for we we found in the past that for some members, especially in the RGC side.
Okay, thank you, thank you, Chairman. Let me take the second part first. As I said, we treated individual individual tickets as a as a a unit of procurement. But in securing the best price, we approached five travel agents for each ticket.
誒，仲仲有咧，你知每一張ticket嘅coding咧都會有唔同嘅，有有啲有啲誒學者為我要將可以三個月內都可以轉multiple changes都唔使錢嘅，咁有啲如果你fix死咗係嗰嗰一日出發嘅又唔同喎，噉你哋嗰個誒budget？
誒誒AirTicket而容許佢哋帶佢嘅誒先生太太或者伴侶，咁呢個做法又係咪真係誒其他嘅同類機構都可以認可噉樣做法嘅咧？即係有兩個問題，個採購嗰個機票嗰個誒程序係點樣同？
Dr. Richard Amat, you understand the question? Yes. Good. I thank you. I thank Chairman. Thank you for the question. For the procurement practice, we have historically treated every air ticket as a as a unit of procurement, every single one, because our thinking is that individual
Overseas members' journeys can be can start and finish in different places because of their timetable. So we treated everyone as an individual item. We recognise that that may not be best practice, and we're more than happy. In fact, I've started discussions with the government logistics department to get advice about procurement of.
In batching them, we're able to secure a better price for a for a package of tickets. Whether it's practical, because of the the late itinerary changes, but we're more than happy to take advice from those who know more about procurement than we do, and to to take up the advice and the recommendations of of the audit. Now, as far as the
The member's home location to Hong Kong—that's that's set in stone. And if if they can procure two tickets at a cheaper rate within that themselves within that that overall budget, we allow it. If other organisations do it, I don't know. Certainly, other overseas organisations do it.
嘢。
係。
所以， anything excess，  they pay for it。
whatever， it's always subject to that financial limit。
嘅誒現任嘅質保局嘅成員啦，七名。
Sometimes in batches, but often one at a time, depending on the location.
Between and that becomes a financial between the that destination and Hong Kong. Correct.
啊，主席，我諗我暫時係冇問題，我畀其他委員發問。唔該曬，唔該曬啊！
de facto yes, because I think in those cases we would almost always ask the member to procure the ticket himself up to the financial limit.
And that would cost thirty thousand. So did you get any reimbursement from that academic for the extra ten thousand dollars? That's my question, Doctor Richard.
Everything, the budget. You're quite right. is It seems chaotic, but the overall, the overriding.
Absolutely. So the the rules is very simple. That from the the port of origin, the cheapest price for business class. Yes.
前教資會嘅成員同埋百名前質保股嘅成員獲委任嘅時候，去提交嗰二十六份嘅利益登記表。咁其實呢個呢個問題其實點解會係咁？會唔會牽涉到誒有利益衝突啊？
budgetary ceiling is the cheapest available flight from the the member's declared home place, whether it's New York or London, or Shanghai and Hong Kong. That's a financial budget limit. If there are variations within the ticket that they they wish to procure because they're going side trips or or
咁即係話，而家你哋係冇follow任何嘅即係物流處嘅嘅嘅程序或者誒指引，一即即係你哋而家係做緊你哋自己個套噉，我嘅解讀係啱唔啱？不如你話你自己嗱，當然我頭先聽到就話每一個每一宗嘅機票，因為嗰個誒學者都係有唔同嘅需。
又或者有唔同嘅地方去嚟，誒日期又唔同，所以你就當每一張或者每一套機票咧，都係一個separate procurement誒。咁但係噉樣樣嘅情況底下，可能真係你哋會誒令到嗰個機票價格係會真係誒調調高咗，因為你每次都係買一張或者兩張機票啦，變咗。
誒噉，第二樣嘢我就想問啦。你就算你話一張機票都好咧，你究竟你係嘣一聲就揾你相熟嘅travel agent去買啊，抑或你都係嘣一聲都要分誒做一個誒價錢嘅comparison，即係話你要揾三四個唔同嘅agent去睇睇嗰張ticket啦，誒。
That that means the the academics will pay you back for the extra or what? If if say the financial limit is twenty thousand dollars for a ticket, and he he he he want to, for example, get a ticket which will allow him to to stay over when on the return leg.
所以。
啊。
但。
唔知。
八。
睇睇個單筒咧。
所以我冇聽到問題，sorry sir。
yes，唔係佢係個半。
Doctor Chilama，聽過聽過聽過。
唔係，我我再我再repeat，page forty seven啊。
I'm guessing the question is where these what happened to these these declaration of interests form? The problem is we can't locate them.
Well, I've heard part of the question, which is that for some members the conflict of interest one had not been located. That's as far as my translation got.
咁誒噉，其實咧，審計處揾咗呢個問題出嚟之後咧，佢哋教資會知道有冇話仲重新去走去揾翻，即係問翻嗰廿六嗰個嗰廿六個理理登記表出嚟，有冇再去尋求翻呢個問題出嚟咧？佢check清咗。
the the conflict of interest forms that we could not locate are the are the first tier conflicts of interest which are which are secured from members on their appointment, but there was no no in effect conflict of interest because the second tier was always applied. It's a two tier system.
But then the leading leading question that you could not locate had that been any conflict of interest? Oh, my apologies, I didn't get that part. I'm sorry, sir. In in in effect, there have been no conflicts of interest because remember, we always have the second tier, case by case, item by item declaration.
Yes, we are trying to locate them and we continue to try and locate them. That you cannot locate them, you ask them to resubmit. Oh, yes, I apologise. Yes, of course we will ask them to resubmit and we are in general going to improve the system to a more regular basis. We're all going to. We're also going to compile a.
係有邊位係啊？書員啊，唔該，先我想問問第啊page四啊七頁啦。噉佢誒審計處嗰度咧就話，即係去揾到教資會秘書處咧。而家對麥有冇事啊？係啊，page四啊七頁啦。佢啊審計處就講教資會秘書處咧就未曾揾到咧三名現任嘅教資會嘅成員啦，兩名。
for those reasons.
register。
Dr. Richard.
quickly replied.
咁即係最撈尾，其實呢啲二十六份嘅誒。
你登記表話咧，申報話，即係其實係未曾揾到嘅，係嘛？
誒，你好。誒，Actually，as the same question that Kenneth have asked，可，你just。
對話，關於教學、學習、研究和資金，那些都加到策略，為UGC，但。
A database of each member and their form, so that we can always tell that one is late or not or haven't arrived, and so we can make sure the database is up to speed constantly.
case is now fully up to date with all members' register of interest. But at the time the audit talked to us, we couldn't locate some. That is true. So could you just give us a copy of their updating to satisfy our writing of the report? Certainly. That this 26
Richard, the twenty-six decorated register of interests that are up to date. You still have not. We we haven't located the ones which the audit couldn't find, but they have been they've been updated by all the individual members. That's been received. There's a difference, but the the data be.
Interest have been completed。啊，唔該住。係，係。好嗱，喺page四啊九頁嗰度咧，咁審計署咧，佢係留意到咧有兩名嘅質保局嘅成員咧，其實出席率係好低嘅。噉，其餘出席率咁低嗰啲嘅成員嘅話咧，其實你有冇考慮即係要換咗人去咧？啊，市議員，頭先啊梁議員問。我去問咗條，我唔好意思，唔緊要。
Yes, we've certainly taken into account in all cases of renewal of membership, and we treat poor attendance as a major criterion. When those members' terms of office come up, that'll be very much on the table for consideration. There certainly have been the cases in the past where members have not been renewed for.
O.K.喺喺page四啊九頁嗰度咧，噉啊，審備處就提過啦。佢教資會咧就係冇啊，去準備一啲策略嘅計劃嘅文件嘅。噉嘅意思即係其實你哋係即係冇白紙一字，平時寫低落嚟嘅，冇文件記錄嘅。噉你點樣去確保到第日嗰啲工作嘅話咧，可以如恆噉樣進行啊？
I thank you, Chairman. Through you, as I think we replied to the audit, we do not have a single document labelled strategic plan. But the UGC has many, many strategies. These are encapsulated in various strategic major documents, like our aspirations for.
呢次。
take your time, take your time.
需要太耐嘅，因為佢哋六月、四月、六月、九月，我相信呢啲年度裏邊，我嘅。
高級嘅同事咧，去得到個confirmation啦，即係去確認啦，或者誒，即係如果你咁個機構點樣監管咧？如果唔跟住原則嘅話，
嚇，我係寫個report，覺得我會考慮依一點嘅嚇。係唔該，主席。啊，另外喺page五廿四嗰度啦，咁審計署咧，佢就話即係喺誒發現你哋。
The future of higher education report, our governance report, our discussion forums with between members and heads of departments, of which there were four, and which tried to attempt to map out the future of Hong Kong higher education for 2020 and beyond, then broke into longer and different dialogue.
或者啊，局長，你想唔想答啊？你點睇依個問題？而係你想睇到依個問題嗰個嗰個。
情況係點出嚟？頭先啊，Deputy都講咗佢哋會做，噉你冇一個時間限制住佢哋想點做，幾時可以去做？因為依個都好重要嘅，依個strategy plan啊，喺依個四點十嗰度都提出嚟啊。係，啊多謝主席。頭先啊，Richard都有提到，Richard話agree嘅一個比較全。
前面啲嘅誒一個一個誒策略文件係需要嘅，咁所以咧就U.G.C Secretary都agree咗咧，佢哋將put it together，佢變咗係一個single set of document噉嘅形式出現咧，就以後咧做reference會易好多。咁而且將會咧帶翻去畀U.G.C，我相信呢個時間唔會。
感覺咧，我嘅要求咧，希望佢能夠做得到八N六D E啊。即係有一個噉嘅策略嘅計劃喺度啊，局長會唔會配合到你整體嗰個誒，即係誒tertiary education下誒嗰個你哋嗰個政策咧，係冇撇咗佢哋，你點監察都？
佢哋同你哋有冇行唔同嘅路線啊？咁喺度，因為都係你畀筆錢過去嗰邊㗎嘛。其實咧就即係我都睇到咧啊，以往嘅做法，因為有唔同嘅時段咧，有唔同嘅重要嘅一啲嘅計劃，例如try and funding嗰時候咧，我哋都有唔同嘅文件交交。
旺嘅，所以我都睇得到整體嗰個對呢個策略嗰個配合，每一年嘅呢個施政報告裏邊提到有關嘅時候咧，都會出現咗喺有關嘅UGC嘅文件裏邊。不過頭先主席提到個好同埋呢個委員會反應好嘅時候咧，put it together in one set of document，呢個咧就會個patch就會好多，我覺得可以做。
做法嘅能力都consistent，例如最近嘅governance report，其他方面睇到咧，佢都依住曬整體嗰個策略去做嘅。多謝主席。喺度多謝誒誒呢個審計處長咧，你提呢個意見咧，即係整體對成個結構嗰個即係前前景去點睇咧，係係重要嘅喺度。
fair's。
作為一個unit of procurement。
委員會，那監察。
We've now been advised that because.
Bundle of ear tickets in the same are for the same purpose.
If you explain in a way rather than looking at separate units.
to director of audit staff, the way that that how this turns out, because you are inviting quite a lot of scholars from different areas at different time, commanding different
即係喺誒會議開支嘅時候咧，嗰啲秘書處咧佢採購工作嘅時候咧係唔依循咧佢哋個原則同埋規定嘅。咁其實如果秘書處唔依循嗰個原則同埋規定嘅話咧，即係佢哋需唔需要事前係同你哋上司有特別去申請啊？有話鋪。
化有確認啊，定係即係點樣去監管嗰啲秘書處工作咧？啊，一説完啦，麻煩咧，因為有佢哋都要有啲翻譯嘅，麻煩你唔好用邊個頁數，因為我哋睇中文同埋睇英文咧個頁數係唔同嘅。你用邊個paragraph？四個段，所以係四點二二段咧，應該係。係啊，唔該曬你。四點咁咧，佢哋可以。
睇同時睇埋咧，噉就會好啲。係唔該曬。四點二段噉啊，重新啦嚇，即係審計署嗰邊講咧，就係話發現嗰教資會秘書處咧，有陣時喺採購工作嘅時候咧，佢就係唔跟從咧，即係誒上述嘅原則啦，同埋規定去做嘅。咁如果唔跟從，佢哋唔跟從嗰啲原則嘅話咧，佢哋需唔需要同佢哋嘅上司啊，或者更高？
Well, thanks, gentlemen. In terms of procurement, as I said, UGC is more than happy to update its practices in consultation with those colleagues and government departments who advise on procurement. More than happy to do that. The UGC also has a general administration and management.
Operational business of the secretariat, and of course they would be advised of of the issues and have been already about that have come up through the audit, and I'm sure they will going forward they will make sure that my colleagues and I are able to demonstrate that that all of these.
Issues that have been brought up and are attended to, and systems are put in place to make sure that they don't they don't fail to meet government standards in the future. The question, as Mr. Se was asked, the honourable Se was asking, is the four two two that you are not abiding to the principles set up.
In terms of procurement, but then the question is not that there is no guideline nor principles, but you didn't follow the principles. So can you explain first why you didn't follow the principles making this procurement? And secondly, how you you have answered the second question is that you will try.
要做，呃，In fact, you have to do it. 嗯，係啊，主席唔該。Can you answer that on those two bases? Okay. Well, on the first question, the the the the difference at issue about procurement of air tickets was that we in our practice had had viewed a single air.
Irrespective of different journeys, then it should be it should be dealt with in a different different method. And the the value of of a bundle of tickets would have to be treated in a different way. For example, we may have to to go to tender. Now, more than happy, we are more than happy to discuss that with GLD. We we started.
Earlier already, and there are still issues because air tickets are complex things. But in principle, we are more than happy to go forward with it. But the problem we didn't comply was a difference of perception of the unit of procurement, which is quite a moot point. Whether a single ticket is a is an item or whether it is a bundle of tickets, that was the difference. Wouldn't it be better
that because the time of travelling is different, because there's high time and low low time that commands different fare, and because of the different destination that our judges come from, coming from different time, so that is very difficult for you to come sort of.
之前咪有。
但你必須。
復咗翻嚟喺Gen九係咪Gen九啊？Gen九有二千二千幾啊？二千九啊？定二千二千？幾多percent到啊？大概幾多percent到啊？
Because the honourable was asking that we have a duty to ensure that every cent of public money is spent wisely and not thrown away to waste.
跟進嗰個問題咧，就係講噉，其實佢哋有幾多嗰啲真係過嚟讀書誒，攞咗呢學位嘅學生，係喺香港度繼續留喺度啊嘛。咁所以即係上一次我問嘅答案，其實佢係即係有冇畀到我哋嘅。
follow the government logistic and procurement guideline. So you need to have a flexibility to draw up your guideline. Because if you say blind blindly follow the government, you are asking for more trouble in future. So I think it's better to explain, which you haven't explained to.
So, so I think on that basis you explain, and then you devise the honourable, you can devise a system that you can follow, and with the in that guideline, because the education bureau give you quite a a free hand in your own administration, but we not here that we can ask you to follow.
Have a system that you can work. So if you answer us that you follow everything that the government does, then you you're asking for more trouble because we will write down in our report and in future they will go and look into your follow up report. And this is no end.
So I think it's better with your experience, with your, with the circumstances that you are subjected to, that you devise and advise us in due course before we write the report. Yes, you understand the question, the importance. I understand the question. I understand the importance. If I
Maybe I'm misinformed or miscommunicated with members. We have some complex processes that don't fit neatly into government systems. What we are prepared to do is to take advice from in terms of best practice. We may not be experts in procurement generally. We have some problems with procurement. We are ready.
Entering discussions with those who are in the procurement business, where we explain our problems and they explain the higher-level issues, and we'll come to a compromise, I'm sure, and devise an improved system which UGC will be able to follow, which meets our needs and meets as closely as possible the extant government guidelines.
主席係唔該，主席啊！呢個問題，我想問阿阿局長嘅，因為其實上一次喺個會度，其實都都問過啦。即係就喺paragraph嗰度啊，四點三二段嗰度咧，即係審教處咧，佢就講即係其實佢分析到嘅嗰啲每一間大學嘅話咧，即係非本地嘅學生嗰啲組合咧，其實內地生咧，其
就係佔嗰個比例，其實就好大啦，係咪？噉我喺上次其實個會都提過，即係如果你係呢一類嘅誒誒同學過嚟香港，即係如果你第日誒繼續留喺香港，當然對我哋香港係一件好事啦。噉樣咁上一次又問過，即係局長佢哋有冇啲數啊？即係佢哋有幾多percent其實留翻喺度？佢哋有冇復康翻嚟畀我哋㗎？有有。
又睇睇誒J六啊，J六嚇，你睇睇J六。我讀個誒，阿局長你睇翻J六就答到個問題㗎啦。係啊，喺一五一六學年咧，就係直至到呢一個一六年六月為止咧，有二千六百八十五名係呢一個學士學位資歷嘅新。
申請人係留喺香港嘅，佔幾多percent度啊？啊，幾percent？佔幾多percent度啊？嗰啲國國內新嗰啲嚟咗香港嘅話，即係嗰啲博士學位嗰啲嚇。我聽下阿阿巴仁答答。係啊。係，多謝主席。書長。誒，我哋而家手頭上有嗰個數字，就係一個確實嗰個學生人數嗰個數字。嗯嗯。但係因為
呢啲數字我哋都係由入境處嗰方面提供，佢哋就冇一個分項，即係話幾多係嚟自內地，幾多係嚟自其他地方嘅，嚇嚇即係冇一個噉嘅統計要求。我哋一個統計嗰個噉。我上一次啊，主席，所以我上一次我問個問題問得好清楚，因為點解咧？其實因為講緊喺誒內地嚟嘅同學，其實佢佔咗個數量好大啊嘛。二零一零年嘅
時候佔咗成八十七個percent，二零一五年嘅時候佔咗七十個percent。即係香港有啲市民嘅話咧，其實佢哋係憂慮會唔會佔用咗你本地嘅啊同學嗰啲學位咧噉樣噉。其實署方講，或者其實有啲市民都講啊，唔係嘅，即係嗰啲內地嘅朋友，佢哋人才噉，其實留翻喺度都係對香港係好事嘅。所以我上一次。
嗱喺Gen六嗰度咧，佢畀咗答話即係噉啊！冇冇，我哋唔需要喺度啊！即係再叫局長，我哋再問問你而家要求嗰個問題，再畀阿局長等有啲時間，因為都有好多數字佢哋要揾嘅。O K，得我好唔好啊？阿局長，我諗咁處理好唔好？因為你喺Gen六嗰度講咗有二千六百個。
咧，work with一啲畢業生嘅。
有冇有冇定期去做呢樣嘢嘅？
但係咧，嗰啲教職員嗰啲組合嘅資料咧，即係好似佢哋啲資歷啊、經驗啊，喺邊個國家噉樣咧，就其實咧就教資會咧就誒。
四點三四段嗰度啦。咁審計處嘅留意到咧，即係教資會佢備資處定期咧，其實佢收集嗰啲學生咧嗰個組合嗰啲資料嘅，噉就誒。
即係個方向其實都係咁咯，即係要同啲香港市民交代。我相信其實即係即係點樣留得翻佢哋喺度嘅話咧，即係都可以令到一啲誒誒市民明白啊！嗰啲學位去邊度，啲錢擺咗邊。啊，仲有個問題啫，誒誒，主席就啊。
但係二千六百個樹源問你咧，呢二千六百個percentage係乜嘢咧？係有冇影響到本地嘅學生，而係佢哋用咗幾年去讀佢哋嘅博士學位，而本地學生被誒冇冇咗依個機會，而係依班人係咪對香港整體畢咗業留喺香港度係可以對我哋貢獻？
即係我係會再問過你好冇？好啊！阿阿樹，我係咁咁問過去啦，同埋即係佢答喺即係六個答嗰度係有少少唔同啊。係多謝主席，多謝議員嘅提問。啊，我上次都提到咧，就係因為呢啲資料咧係我哋透過呢個係Immigration Department係攞到出嚟，而且個data。
喺base上邊咧，佢有冇track嗰度嘅origin咧？呢個係重要嘅一個step one嚟嘅。但係呢部分咧，成咧我理解，from啊副秘書長咧就係呢一個咧immigration department咧未能夠畀到我哋入壁單，同埋佢有冇呢個壁單？因為好多時香港嘅制度有時咧，佢問嗰啲origin嘅data嗰時咧，有啲時佢唔攞嘅，因為呢個唔係佢主要範圍。
係啊！咪prove佢整個政策就話咧，喺香港畢業嘅undergraduate學生咧，可以一年時間留喺度，未有工作嘅時候咧，等佢揾機會去contribute。呢個就係政策嗰個層面做嘅。咁如果我哋以後咧稍後時間，如果if government level能夠多啲逼單嘅時候咧，我一定會come back話翻畀大家聽。
特別班嘅數字，即係主席問個問題咧幾貼切嘅，即係影影睇影響咗香港學生誒畢業學生好誒呢個格誒呢個學士學生或者係呢博士學生。咁咧，我諗喺或者你啲啲而家你都係講提出多問一個個答係案嗰度係你哋。
冇啲，或者將來你可以喺呢一方面咧配合阿邵議員誒要求嗰個問題嚟睇，因為呢個對你哋個我哋資源用落去誒我誒外地嘅學生誒嗰個。主席，我補充一點啊，係就誒我哋而家開展咗，因為以往我哋冇check同埋冇。
喺啲香港畢業之後，去翻內地其他地方嗰啲。而家我哋開展咗咧，就同一啲嗰啲學生嘅呢個online唔同大學嘅online開始有啲新嘅網絡。我哋希望透過網絡咧，加強翻我哋知道咧，同佢哋嘅接觸，而鼓勵佢哋繼續翻翻嚟香港貢獻呢部分，我哋進行緊嘅。啊！
啱啱大部分嘅呢個組織嘅number咧，我哋都有咗個接觸面，但係咧要慢一步一步去做，因為咧有部分已經有自己一個業啊，其他部分我哋要揾出原因，點可以吸引佢留喺度繼續contribute呢部分嘅，所以我哋開展咗第一部分嘅networking嗰部分主題。O.K.好，good，非常非常之好，局。
啊，局長，你想答或者因為大學嘅自主係你哋唔應該去誒幹預嘅，同埋去大學嘅選擇佢哋嗰啲教教職員咧，你哋都冇參與喺度㗎，係咪啊？啊啊，我哋整體就噉樣嘅，因為咧就係呢一個係聘用人員咧係呢個大學嘅。
自主範圍嚟㗎，咁當然啦，嗰個國際化嗰個政策嘅方向係喺度嘅，咁所以咧就呢個係教師會都有一係列嘅工作做，或者我想請阿Richard詳細啲解釋一下喺國際化裏邊嘅時候咧，佢嗰個人員啊，其他方面點樣處理？Yes, Richard, do you understand the question?
Yes, I believe so. I mean, as the secretary said, the universities are autonomous in terms of hiring faculty and staff, and that's part of UGC's job is to protect that. That said, as part of the internationalisation discussion, it would be helpful if we had if we had data about the range.
係。
Richard。
誒，我想問誒。
係就誒，關於。
for the sector, for the sector as a whole, the the breakdown and the
你 have answered that you could not find. The question now is, what have you done?
啊，唔該啊，主席。就誒，我我首先想跟進翻咧報告入邊四點六段啊。
In to investigate the loss of this twenty-six declaration of interest. Well.
Collect relevant data and publish it. We'll be happy to do so. But you you ask for figures, but you're not setting a policy.
教資會秘書處咧就未能夠找到咧誒若干委員嘅二二十六份利益申報表個問題。
In a sense, in searching for them, there's been an inquiry as to what what went wrong because we can we've investigated all our files to find if they've been misfiled or, for example, so we have we have.
教資會秘書處嗰邊咧，有冇就呢個事件咧進行個內部嘅調查，揾出呢二十六份利益登記表唔見咗嘅原因咧？
the profile of the faculty population across the sector in terms of internationalisation, and it's something we've agreed to look into. We'll happily talk to the universities and see if they can see how they feel about that, and if we can.
Such unlike students, you have a twenty percent policy, but in terms of recruitment, there's no policy. But you you only indicate that there is a trend for internationalisation. I think you have to be very careful in your question, because the university.
Autonomy, especially the hiring of of teaching staff, must remain within the realm of the university. I hope that that is not what, because I just want to make sure that you understand that in your answer. Yes, thank you, chairman. May I just be clear? I am very aware of the.
敏感度， of universities in their hiring and recruitment of students, and I would protect that. So, in in my conversations with the university, it'll be about data. It'll not be about interfering with. 好嘅，嚇。答咗答咗你問題啦，嚇。得唔該曬主席㗎嚇。有冇其他問題啊？阿卓。
即係。
每頁文件都要走。
唔係生活喺一個即係。
冇人為因素喺入邊。
或是個系統， non-existent。 There's
佢話：，Have you investigate why such things happen？
去揾出個成因。Okay, you understand the question now? I do understand the question. Thank you. Well, the the the the reason is there was a system flaw.
啊！啊，主席，我我想問下乜嘢叫做即係制度嘅即係錯誤咧？噉樣即係係咩嘅具體情況導致係咁咧？
There's a system flaw. The fact that we can't find it means that there is a system flaw. The system flaw is that a human error, the staff error, that contributed to the failure of that system.
which we're trying to fix by creating a database and register of of the registers of interest. That's our improvement to our previous system, which was not as good as it should have been.
We have undertaken a thorough search to try and find the the missing forms. However, we've also, as I said earlier, obtained new forms for those from those 26 that are missing. No, you haven't answered the question. You search, but that doesn't mean that the question being answered.
啊！It's the system rather than the documents. Okay, yes.係啊，我我而家唔係問佢有冇做呢個search啊，即係呢個一定佢一定會去揾啦。如果唔係都唔知揾唔到啦。咁但係揾唔到之後點解點解有噉嘅事咧？你有冇做呢個調查？
It's very specific. Yes, there is a system, but if there's a system flaw, it seems to me automatically those who designed the system or failed to do so are at fault. Because he asked a very valid question that you are going, you promise that you're going to review the system, but the honourable lamb asked if you don't know what the
What went wrong with the system? How can you improve it? This is the question. I understand, Chairman. Thank you for that. As part of the designing of a new system, we will have a review of the old system and talk to those individuals who are currently involved to see how what the flaw was and improve on that.
我 think that's a reasonable way forward。啊，主席，我聽到即係現在佢嘅解釋咧，似乎佢都唔知道究竟點解唔見咗嗰二十六份嘅利益申報表。一尾就話係呢個system fault。但係呢呢個即係制度嘅嘢咧，佢即係我哋而家。
而你揾唔翻啲證據出嚟咧，即係第一。
我Fully understand and accept it, and agree.而而我即係。
I would agree. Yeah, good. Okay.即係你其實一開頭咁答咪好咯。
Yo, thank you. Well, I don't know how to answer that exactly. There's a paperless or a papered.
即係呢個唔係純粹你所講制度嘅問題，係有人為嘅過失問題，你同唔同意啊？
我咯，因為我我理解啦，呢啲嘅申報表應該都係有一個，即係。
文件喺度㗎嘛？唔係純粹係electronic㗎嘛？係咪？定係即係先答呢個？不如係咪全部都係電子嘅文件？定係有paper嘅？有文字？有有文字？有紙嘅？Richard。
最少就係一個嚴重嘅失職啦。第二可能會令人懷疑，其實誒教資會係唔係有人去收埋咗呢啲證據，係好不利嘅狀況。你你明白嗎？
paper，所以你answer，that係paper。係paper system。and，then，the，question，is，having，returned，the，paper，then，it，went，into，your，system。yes。the，system，somehow，between，the，return，of，the，papered，declaration，of，interest，it，get，lost。
即係兜咗大輪嗱。誒，我我想講咧，呢個係誒重要嘅點解咧？因為呢啲利益申報嘅記錄啊，係日後如果有人有利益衝突嘅情況，呢啲記錄就係擺上法庭嘅證據之一嚟嘅。
電影嘅橋段當中，全部都係電腦控制我哋生活㗎嘛？係有人去管住嗰個制度㗎嘛？去參與個制度㗎嘛？係咪？如果喺廉署啊，即係你唔見咗個花喎，即係大鑊啊！真係又又即係誒嗰個房第一步守到去最多咩一步？
噉你係有手嘅，但係你最重要一樣嘢係揾出個問題係出自邊度啊？嘛，邊個監管人員係負責睇住個制度，而佢係睇唔住，或者個制度本身係有問題。但我我唔覺得即係個制度本身會有問題，係令到嗰啲記錄自動會消失咗。
或未not be received，你唔知。呢個呢個係個問題。呢個係個
Richard, you understand the comments? It's very valid comments. I understand the comment, and if I may, through you, chairman, I'll very much take that into account in the. The purpose of PAC auditors' report and PAC reports are for looking. It's not that we want to pinpoint.
Where you who who does it wrong and and punishment? It's not that, but the whole question you must know what went wrong so that you can improve. We are all. That's just what the whole PAC public hearings and reports are all about: forelooking that we do not commit the same error again. Do you understand?
即係比較難接受啊！秘書長嘅解釋咧，就係即係似乎到現在佢都未深刻咁吸取呢個教訓，去揾出成件事嘅成因，同埋要負責要負責嘅即係誒相關嘅職員。
同埋跟進嗰個即係工作係點樣？我我明你會有嗰個制度嘅檢討，但係你個檢討嘅前設係你要瞭解咗過往問題嘅根源喺邊度先啊嘛？係咪可能係制度加人為，可能係人為等等嘅問題，你要睇一睇咯。即係呢個係我少少。
工作。
B嗰段啦。
啊，twenty twelve。
其實我嗰個問題咧，就係。
嘅誒意見啦，咁誒第二個咧就係我我想問埋咧，都係四點六段誒。
That you only came in. What what year you came in? And we're talking of the period between 2012, 12, 2015, 16. When did you join?
噉我見到咧就話誒，研資局嘅成員咧就誒要提交每年提交最新嘅資料嘅理登記表。
啊！主席就其實我唔唔係好，佢唔係好説服到我點解會有兩套即係制度。不過無論如何，佢現在都即係肯挖一翻啦。噉我我我最後想問咧。
博士同埋碩士學位咧，係並沒有咧任何嘅誒限制，畀外地生嚟申請嘅，而當中主要係內地生啦。噉我我嗰個問題就係。
點解誒個文件係誒定係我上次冇冇問到？定係點解咧？就碩士同埋博士個學位誒留翻喺香港嘅畢業生嘅人數係幾多咧？即係政府有冇呢個資料咧？
有有關呢個誒頭先講到阿邵議員提過Jan Six嗰個問題啊，係就誒嗰二千六個係啦係啦，第三點嗰個就二千六百八十五個持有學士學位資歷嘅申請人獲準在港就業。
但係，教資會同埋教資會小組委員會同埋質保局嘅成員咧，就無需遵守有關嘅規定。嗱，我明白你哋而家改緊即係有關嘅規定㗎啦。但係點解會有兩套標準喺即係相關嘅機構嗰度咧？
林議員頭先答咗嘅，佢答咗，因為嗰個R.G.C.同埋呢個U.G.C.咧係嗰個嗰個，因為佢哋嘅要求啊、制度啊各方面唔同，唔係唔係代表佢啱與唔啱，但係佢哋一即係瞭解到呢個問題，同埋佢已經畀咗時間表，頭先阿梁議員問嘅問題咧答咗佢。咁誒誒，我睇下有冇。
補充啦，好冇。Richard，你你有answered that questions， but if you have anything further to add, which to the question is asked in a different way. I believe you summarised my answer very properly. And secondly, I think you also you should advise us.
哦，所以你 join at end of this is the period that you were in。 yes。 so I think so I think it's something that you should really, as the honourable learned that you should really review the system and come up with a proposal to be tabled to us of how you in you intend to improve it. okay。 happy to do that。好啊。
我哋上一次會議討論嘅時候咧，其實唔單止係講緊學士學位嘅問題嘅，亦都係提及個碩士誒以至博士嘅課程嘅問題。而呢一樣嘢咧，吳克劍局長咧係誒，亦都即係喺本會誒解釋過。
問題係。
主席誒。
都係香港嘅資源，而
提兩件事咧，呢個嗰個性質有少少唔同，主席。
噉嘅情況底下，如果冇一個數字係誒？
香港嘅學生咧，係要同全世界，尤其係內，即係主要係嚟自內地嘅學生去競爭。
第二咧，呢啲學生嚟到嗰陣時咧，除咗係自己嘅研究之外咧，佢係做一啲嘅教學嘅工作嘅，所以佢唔係淨係純粹嚟研究。
知一個即係一般嘅表述嚟啫嘛，係咪？噉你覺得係咪應該要做翻一個完備嘅統計啊？而呢啲統計，即係啊主席，我唔覺得做唔到咯。
因為你碩士同埋博士生咧，係冇一個誒限額畀佢哋嘅，即係無限額畀佢入嚟讀嘅。即係以我上次對阿局長回覆我哋嘅理解啦。
啊！多謝主席。頭先我都提咗咧，就係咧，我哋冇track到佢哋啊。呢個碩士同埋博士生誒，只係話咧係一啲內地生留喺香港嗰個咧immigration department嘅數據。
教育局或者其他政府部門啦，去誒長期睇住呢啲人士究竟有幾多會係未來誒長期或者係一段時間留喺香港？
喺噉嘅情況底下咧，我哋即係投入好多嘅資源畀呢啲誒外地生啦，而主要係內地嚟嘅學生誒，畀佢哋嚟讀書好、研究好、教學好。
因為咧，特別係啲研究型嘅呢一個碩士同埋博士生咧，有時佢啲研究計劃咧喺香港進咗一部分，然之後咧喺其他地方係另外一部分。好多時候咧，佢離開咗香港第二部分或第三部分嘅研究嗰陣咧，唔等於佢咧係斷咗香港嗰個部分。
第四個原因個部分咧，就佢哋嚟到嗰陣咧，佢帶入咗好多嘅研究嘅範疇，香港以往係冇嘅。咁所以咧幾個做法之餘咧，我哋覺得咧，佢哋對香港應該有貢獻，所以咧我哋都係歡迎咧佢哋儘量留喺度，係比較大嘅自由度。呢個就係個背景。多謝主席。係啊，林議員嗱。
我我而家唔係誒質疑緊有關即係嘅誒碩士生啦、博士生啦誒喺香港嘅時候，或者係誒離開咗香港繼續同香港有關嘅研究對香港嘅貢獻係點樣樣？呢個我冇質疑。嗯，我嗰個問。
對香港實質上佢係從事咩嘅工作，有乜嘢嘅貢獻？你係評估唔到本身你個政策究竟個成效有幾大嘅？即係當然你頭先講嘅係，但係呢個唔係量化嘅統計嚟㗎嘛？係啊，局長，你以你嘅認。
局長。
數字係即係相當唔理想咧，所以唔去攞咧。
詳細啲咧，回應翻有關呢個咧係內地生嘅問題。啊，副秘書長。
啊啊啊！主席冇錯係，就誒頭先啊局長講話誒。
其實係揾到㗎，你點解係要透過一啲即係唔係官方嘅途徑去攞一啲可能係唔全面嘅統計資料咧？噉樣即係你明明可以做得到，點解唔做啊？定係？
去嘅，而係你用咗咁多資源，佢哋又冇冇一啲數字喺度。嚇，依班人我哋嘥咗用咗咁多錢去培養佢哋，佢哋留喺度，而家佢就想問，知道有幾多依啲人留喺度，好唔好啊？
現定係唔係嘅，已經去咗其他地方去誒誒做科研嘅，去賺錢嘅噉樣。即係我覺得係誒，即係噉樣嘅公堂嘅使用咧，唔係好恰當啦，主席。阿局長，你聽到阿林議員嘅意見啊？嚇，我可唔可以？可以可以。翻少少。
係多謝主席。啊，我提一提翻咧，就係咧啊，呢個一個開始咗。頭先我咧答另外一位議員嘅時候，我提到咧，就係我哋已經開展咗同一啲有關嘅一啲嘅組織咧，畢業生組織咧，開始做一啲比較密切嘅聯繫，作為一個起步點去跟進。但係咧，我想就請呢個係勞庫別處長咧。
我哋真係而家講緊係碩士同埋呢個博士生啊。係，多謝主席。誒頭先誒議員有提到就係話點解我哋喺今次嗰個附誒附交嗰個文件上邊冇提到話碩士生同埋博士生嗰個就業嗰個情況咧？最主要就因為誒我哋喺上次收到誒著物委員會誒嗰封。
信裏邊C嗰部分所問我哋個資料咧，就係問誒學士學位嘅畢業生嗰個就業情況。所以我哋今次提供嗰個資料只係限於嗰度。但係我我明白到阿林議員都好關注碩士同埋博士生非本地嗰個碩士博士生嗰個就業情況。我哋喺會後，我哋會盡快係將有關嘅資料係提供翻嘅。好啊。
因為點解咧？因為阿林議問得好對嘅，因為你啲碩士生同埋博士生咧，係一般嘅收費咧，同畀香港學生都一樣嘅。即使我哋啲誒誒非學非呢個唔係呢個誒undergraduate，即係誒呢個啊學士生咧，佢哋。
畀十一萬幾嘅，我哋啲本地學生就畀四萬幾嘅。但係當佢去讀碩士同埋呢個博士咧，佢哋都一樣係畀翻香港市民。所以佢咁問，同我話要問呢個唔係一個政策嘅問題，問個資，因為恆工兩值嘅角度。如果你用咗用翻一樣噉嘅錢，冇收多咗。
答阿邵議員嘅時候已經講咗話會同一啲畢業生嘅組織，即係校友會啊等等聯係啦。其實我覺得好奇怪咯，啊主席，因為即係呢啲數字其實官方係應該要揾得到㗎嘛。嗱，你無論同誒入境處啦，或者係同誒大學有關方面啦。
點解咧？陸昌，你聽到啊？林議員嘅意見，或者誒，你哋翻去攞咗啲數字先畀我哋，好冇？好啊，好啊，唔需要喺度答啦。因為你都冇喺度，冇冇資料喺度，好嘛？魏長啊啊啊！主席，我我最後一點意見啫，就誒，關於碩士同埋博士生個。
嗰個問題咧，因為而家係無上限收呢個海外生，即係包括內地生啦。誒，其實你係咪應該要諗一諗？我哋香港個科研人才成日話缺乏呢一方面，係唔係應該要畀本地生有相當嘅機會喺誒碩士或者博士學位，或者你話？
海外生哇，好好尖端嘅，都畀個機會大家一齊合作學習，係嘛？即係噉樣對香港本地科研嘅人才嘅培育係重要㗎嘛？就唔係而家都唔知道究竟有幾多誒誒外地生，主要外地生嚟到香港讀完書，有幾多留喺度繼續貢。
多謝，有冇其他問題？
我哋會有繼續問問題，先寫我哋報告。Kenneth有冇需要？
我根本喺香港都好難競爭啊！佢放棄呢個競爭啦，出去做嘢啦，或者佢被逼。
Very fruitful meeting, and thank you for the preparation, and thank you強，多謝曬你哋咧嚇，唔該曬啊，三位處長嚇，OK，我完咗啦。
我哋個重要性咧就係阿邵語員嗰陣時問你有幾多香喺我哋栽培嘅國內好啊國際學生好，有幾多係留喺香港，而係配合到我哋用嘅資源畀佢哋嚇，好唔好啊？
其實咧就係啊，議員嘅關注係係啱嘅，所以噉嘅大前提之下咧，如果你睇翻呢啲數據咧，本地嘅學生，如果佢小學、中學、大學都喺度完成嘅時候咧，我上次都有回應少少嘅，佢好希望咧係咧喺碩士或者博士時候咧去第啲地。
地方去涉獵嗱，呢個第一個部分，呢個事實嚟嘅。第二部分咧，我哋希望佢留翻低，所以咧越多機會喺度研究嗰時，佢跟住進修嗰時咧，就能夠令到佢留低。整體嚟講咧，本地嘅同學申請入碩士同埋博士生嘅位咧，嗰個成功率咧係。
比外內地生其他咧係高成超過一倍嘅，所以我哋都係鼓勵噉樣做法。當然啦，係整個環境裏邊咧，我哋都係鼓勵佢咧多啲喺香港嘅環境之下咧係作貢獻。呢個都係我哋嗰個方向嚟嘅。多謝主席。啊，主席，如果係咁咧，我就跟進一條啦。你話本地學生嘅。
申請成功率高過外地生一倍，其實呢個係虛假嘅數據嚟嘅。點解咧？因為你唔知道究竟外地生嘅申請數字係幾多嘛，係本地生嘅數字嘅幾多倍啊嘛。如果人哋係好大量嘅外地生嘅申請，本地生見到哇，喺我。
誒誒，要揾其他海外嘅學校，即即係呢個比較係冇意思嘅。你擺個數字出嚟啦，阿局長，究竟香港本地生讀碩士、博士係幾多人數？海外嘅係幾多人數？嗰個成功率先有意思去比較啊嘛。同埋你講話有。
好多學生想去海外讀書，諸如處女係嘅，阿局長。但係亦都有啲人想留喺香港㗎嘛，即係我而家係講緊嗰啲嘛。如果佢本身想讀哈佛啊、耶魯啊、劍橋，都收咗佢噉，嗰啲梗係唔係我個問題嘅所在啦？你唔好成日即係將嗰個問題咧係轉移到。
我係一個即係好好片面嘅情況去回覆咯，唔該，主席，局長啊，誒有好多啲資料你唔需要喺度答嘅，你攞翻啲資料畀我哋，我哋會會會睇好唔好啊？因為因為你頭先講個你去去你要攞翻，如果每間大學嘅碩士博士生有。
幾多香港人啊？香港學生申請而係有幾多成功嘅咧？而係有幾多外國喺誒內地好誒國內國際好有幾多喺度？然後你先可以頭先講嗰個嗰個你嗰個你答案嗰度咧。咁如果你可以畀多啲資料我哋，我哋睇。但係呢個唔係重要。
冇canary，冇我哋可以今次嘅報告可以完咗。如果我哋需要喺Gem六七八嗰啲佢哋問嘅問題，我哋可以用呢個書面問嘅。其他咧誒，你哋有啲資料畀我哋，我哋都會跟進。噉我哋暫時係呢個報告誒個公開聆訊係完咗，但係我。
誒，我都覺得誒，如果有啲乜嘢跟進問題，可以用書面再同各位啊，呼我哋畀書聯絡嘅。我諗即係誒，公開聆訊喺喺呢度可以暫時即係嗰嗰嗰個段落係唔該啊。誒，Doctor Richard，誒啱啊！誒，I like to thank you for hosting the visit to RGC.